All right. So today,
I wanna continue our study and begin a real每
serious mathematical study of the question of periodicity.
Remember that we are essentially identifying the subject of Fourier series with the study每
with the mathematical study of periodicity.
And last time I went on, at some length,about the virtues of periodicity,
about the ubiquitous nature of periodic functions 每
periodic phenomena in the physical world,
and also in the mathematical world.And we made a distinction,
perhaps a little bit artificial but sometimes helpful,
between periodicity in time and periodicity in space.
Those sort of two phenomena seem to be,or often come to you in different forms,
and it＊s sometimes useful in your own headto sort of ask yourself which kind of periodicity are you looking at?
But in all cases actually,
periodicity is associated with the idea of symmetry.
That＊s the topic that will come up from time to time,
and if I don＊t mention it explicitly,
as with many other things in this course,
it＊s one of the things that you should learn to sort of react to or think about yourself每
see what aspects of symmetry are coming up in the problem,
how does a particular problem fit into a more general context because,
as I＊ve said before and will say it again,
one of the wonderful things about this subject is the way it all hangs togetherand
how it can be applied in so many different ways.
All right.
If you understand the general framework and put yourself每
and orient yourself in a certain way,
using the ideas and the techniques of the class,
you＊ll really find how remarkably applicable they can be.
Okay. So I said 每 as I said last time 每as we finished up last time,
when we＊re sort of still just crawling our way out of junior high,
a mathematical course of periodicity is possiblebecause
there are very simple mathematical functions that exhibit periodic behavior,
namely the sine and the cosine.
But that＊s also the problem because periodic phenomena can be very general and very complicated,
and the sine and the cosine are so simple.
So how can you really expect to use the sine and the cosine
to model very general periodic phenomena?
And that＊s really the question I want to address today.
So how could we use such simple functions 每
sine of t and cosine of t每 to model complex periodic phenomena?
Now, first, the general remark is,how high should we aim here?
I mean, how general can we expect this to be?
So how general? All right.
That＊s really the fundamental question here.
And in answering that question,
led both scientists and mathematicians very far from the original areathat they were investigating.
Let me say 每 well, let me say right now, pretty general,
all right.And we＊ll see exactly how general 每
I＊ll try to make that more precise as we develop a little bit more of the terminology thatreally 每
that will apply and allow us to get more careful statements.
But we＊re really aiming quite high here,all right?
And we＊re really hoping to apply these ideas in quite general circumstances.
Now, not all phenomena are periodic.All right.
And even in the case of periodic phenomena,
it may not be a realistic assumption.
I think that＊s importantto realize here what the limits may be,
or how far the limits can be pushed. So not allphenomena,
naturally, although many are, and many interesting ones are periodic.
Andeven periodic phenomena, in some sense,
you＊re making an assumption there that is notreally physically realizable.
So even for periodic phenomena or at least functions that areperiodic in time,
even phenomena 每
soon I think I＊ll start talking in terms of signalsrather than phenomena,
but phenomena sounds a little grander at this point.
Evenphenomena that are periodic in time 每
real phenomena, they just die out eventually.
Weonly observe 每
or at least we only observe something over a finite period of time,
whereas, as mathematical functions, the sine and the cosine go on forever.
All right. As amathematical model, sine and cosine go on forever.
So how can they really be used tomodel to something that dies out?
But a periodic function, sine and cosine 每
all right 每 goon forever, repeating over and over again.
All right.
So in what sense can you really usesines and cosines to model periodic phenomena when a real periodic phenomena 每
whenit really dies out? Well,
that＊ll take us awhile to sort all that out.
Let me just give you oneanswer to this,
and one indication of how general these ideas really are.
And you have ahomework problem that asks you actually to address this mathematically.
All right. So ifyou have a finite 每 you can still use 每
still apply ideas of periodicity,
even if only as anapproximation or even if only as an extra assumption.
So what I mean by that is, asfollows. So suppose a phenomena looks like this.
Suppose the signal looks like 每something like this 每
let me write it over here. So it dies out over a period of time.
So thisis time and there＊s only a finite interval of time 每
it might be very large,
but there＊s only afinite interval of time when the signal is non-
zero. I＊m drawing just as a 每 somehowgeneric signal here.
Well, that＊s not a periodic phenomena; it doesn＊t exhibit periodicbehavior.
But if it dies after a finite 每 outside of a finite interval,
then you can just repeatthe pattern and make it periodic.
All right. Force this 每 you can force periodicity.
That is,by repeating the pattern. You can force extra symmetry.
You can force extra structure tothe problem that＊s not there in the beginning.
So, I mean by this a very simple idea.Here＊s the original signal,
and I just repeat the pattern. So this is the original signal,
theseare maybe, sort of, you know,
extra copies of it that I＊m just inserting artificially,
andextend the function to be periodic and exist for all time.
You may only be interested inthis part of it,
but for mathematical analysis, if you make it periodic,
that＊ll apply to thewhole thing. All right.
This is sometimes called the periodization of a signal.
And it canbe used 每 and it is used 每 to study signals which are non-
periodic to 每 excuse me 每 to usemethods of Fourier series,
and pumpkins is another sort of Fourier analysis to studysignals which are not periodic.
So there＊s actually a homework problem on different sortsof periodization,
and it＊s a technique that comes up in various applications.
All right. Sosee the first problem set, homework one.
Now,
the point is that periodicity and thetechniques for studying periodic phenomena are really pretty general.
All right.
Even ifyou don＊t have a periodic phenomenon,
you can make it periodic,
and perhaps you couldapply the techniques to study the periodized version of it,
and then restrict 每
study thespecial cases of actually where you＊re interested in the function.
All right. So it＊s pretty 每that＊s the point of this remark,
is that the phenomena 每
that you＊re not restricting yourselfso much by insisting that you＊re gonna use sines and cosines,
or you＊re gonna studyperiodic phenomena.
So the study that we＊re gonna make here can be pretty general 每
itcan apply really quite generally. Okay.
Now, let＊s do it. Or let＊s get launched into theprogram.
So, first of all, let＊s fix a period in the discussion.
All right. So we just 每 just tospecialize and fix ideas,
let＊s take 每
let＊s consider periodic phenomena of a given fixedperiod and see what we can say about those;
see how we can model thosemathematically.
So for the discussion,
let＊s fix the period for the discussion.
All right.And there＊s a choice here.
A natural choice would be too high because the sine and thecosine are naturally periodic of period two pi,
but I think for many formulas and for 每 andfor a variety of reasons,
it is more convenient to fix the period to be one.
All right. Sowe＊re gonna look 每 we＊re gonna consider function signals,
which are periodic of periodone. So we＊ll use period one.
That is, we consider signals 每 I＊ll write things as a functionof time,
but again,
it＊s not only periodicity and time that I＊m considering.
All that I＊mgonna say can apply to any sort of periodic phenomena,
so we＊ll consider functions f of tsatisfying 每
f of t plus one is equal to f of t for all t.
All right.
And as the building blocksas the basic model functions,
we scale the sine and the cosine, that is,
we don＊t just lookat sine of t and cosine of t,
we look at sine of two pi t and cosine of two pi t.
So the modelsignals are sine of two pi t,
that has period one, and cosine of two pi t,
that has periodone. All right. Simple enough.
Now,
one very important thing I wanna comment before 每
before we launch into particulars,
is that periodicity is a strong assumption,
and theanalysis of periodicity has a lot of consequences.
If you know 每 if you have a periodicfunction 每
if you know it on an interval of length one,
and any interval of length one,
youknow it everywhere because the pattern repeats.
If you just know a piece of the function,
you know it everywhere. So if we know 每 if we know,
and I say, if we know 每 if weanalyze, if we 每
whatever formulas we derive, and so on, this is an important maxim.
SoI＊ll put it in quotes, ※know.§ To be a sort of generic,
infinite, perfect, God-likeknowledge. So if we know a periodic function,
say period one, on an interval, and not justa particular interval,
but any interval of length one, then we know it everywhere.
Allright. These are all simple remarks. Okay.
These are remarks that you all have seenbefore in various contexts,
but again,
I wanna lay them out because I want you to havethem in your head.
And I want you to be able to pull out the appropriate remark atappropriate time.
And you＊d be amazed how far simple remarks can lead in the analysisof really quite complicated phenomena.
Now, how are we gonna 每
how are we gonnatake such simple functions of sine and cosine individually,
and model very complicatedperiodic phenomena?
That is the sine and the cosine as endlessly fascinating as they maybe,
are just the sine and the cosine. But the fact is,
they can be modified and combined toyield quite general results.
We can modify and combine sine of two pi t,
cosine of two pit,
to model very general periodic phenomena of period one.
Okay. To model generalperiodic signals of,
again, period one. All right. Now, here is the first big idea,
or here＊s away of phrasing the first big idea.
When I talk about modifying and combining 每
well,let＊s first talk about modifying.
And the maxim or the aphorism that goes on 每
goes withwhat I have in mind is, one period,
many frequencies. As far as a big idea 每
one period,many frequencies.
I think you can actually find this in The Dead Sea Scrolls.
Okay. Whatdo I mean, one period, many frequencies?
Well, let me just take a simple example.
Imean, for example, e.g., you have sine of two pi t,
and we know what the graph of thatlooks like.
I＊ll put the graphs over here. It repeats once and it has 每
it＊s a period one; italso has a frequency one that is 每
completes one cycle in one second. So if I think of thisas the time axis,
say, although, again, I＊m thinking in terms of time,
it＊s a very generalmathematical statement.
It repeats exactly once on the interval from zero to one.
Allright.
If I double the frequency and look at sine four pi t 每
all right 每 then that completestwo cycles.
So this is period one, frequency. Sine of four pi t is period one-
half,frequency one 每 frequency two, but period one-
half also means period one. All right. Andthe picture looks like this,
it goes up and down twice 每 [inaudible] 每
it does, in onesecond. All right. Zero, one,
it repeats. One cycle 每
it goes through one cycle in a half asecond,
it goes through two cycles in one second,
so that＊s frequency two. All right.
Butit also has period one because if you consider this as the basic pattern that repeats,
and italso repeats on an interval of length one.
Okay.
It＊s true that it repeats on an intervallength one-
half,
but the signals already contained in interval one-
half, but the whole 每 butthe signal also has a longer period.
All right. It has a shorter period, but it also has alonger period.
And let me do one more. If, for instance,
I look at sine of six pi t, verysimple. All my remarks are very simple.
This is period one-third, this has frequencythree,
but it also has period one. You might think of this as,
I don＊t know, the secondaryperiod, or somehow 每
I don＊t know what exactly the best way of saying it because,
really,
the best description is in terms of frequency not period.
And what does the picture looklike? Well,
this time it has three cycles per second 每
frequency three 每
so that means itgoes up and down three times in one second.
Let＊s see if I can possibly do this. One,
two,three. Good enough. One, zero, and one cycle is in one 每
goes up and down completelyonce in one-third of a second,
then the next third of a second it goes up and down again,
the next third of a second it goes up and down a third time.
But it also has period onebecause if you consider this has the pattern that repeats,
that pattern repeats on an intervalof length one.
Although, in some sense, the true repetition 每
the true period is shorter thanthat. Now,
what about combining them? So that＊s how you can modify 每
and you can dothe same thing with cosine.
That＊s how you modify the function 每 one period,
manyfrequencies. If we combine them together,
I actually have a picture of it here, but I thinkI＊ll just try to sketch it 每
fool that I am. What about the combination?
And when I saycombination, I am thinking of a simple sum.
That is sine of two pi t plus sine of six pi t 每
excuse me 每
sine of four pi t plus sine of six pi t.
All right. What does the graph of thatlook like?
Well, it looks like so. And I＊m gonna sketch this,
and then I＊m gonna 每 I＊llmake 每
I wanna make another comment about this in just a second,
but I actually hadMathematica plot this for me.
It looks something like this, it goes 每
this is plotted on aninterval of length two.
All right. I＊ve plotted it and it goes 每
it＊s kinda nice,
it goes up andthen a little bit like this,
and then it goes up and then down a little bit farther,
and up alittle bit like that, and it goes down 每
that＊s the sound it makes 每 up, down like that,
andthen up 每 excuse me 每 and that＊s not two,
it will be two, and down and up, and then therewe go.
Two. And then it repeats. Here＊s one. All right.
That＊s the sum. Now, what is theperiod of a sum?
The period of the sum is one. All right.
Because although the things of 每
the terms of higher frequency are repeating more rapidly,
the sum can＊t go back to whereit started until the slowest one gets caught up 每
goes to where 每 back to where it started.
All right. The period of the sum is one. One period,
many frequencies. There are threefrequencies in the sum.
One, two, and three. But added together,
there＊s only one period.So in a complicated 每
this is a very important point, and again,
I＊m sure it＊s a point thatyou＊ve seen before.
That＊s why I say one period, many frequency,
and that＊s why forcomplicated periodic phenomena,
it＊s really better, more revealing,
to talk in terms of thefrequencies that might go into it,
rather than the period. You are fixing the period.
You＊refixing the period to have length one.
All right. But you want 每
but you might have a verycomplicated phenomena.
That complicated phenomena, as it turns out,
is gonna be builtup out of sines and cosines of varying frequency.
AS long as the sum has period one, thenwe＊re okay.
One period, many frequencies.
That＊s the aphorism that goes on with this 每
that goes along with this. Now, in fact, what is it 每
what we can do more than just modifythe frequency.
We can also modify the amplitudes separately,
and we can modify thephases of each one of those 每
each one of those terms. So to model complicated,
perhaps,how complicated? We＊ll see.
A complicated signal of period one we can sum 每
we canmodify the amplitude, the frequency,
and the phases of either sines or cosines,
but let mejust stick with the sines 每 of sine of two pi t,
and add up the results. That is, we canconsider something like this.
Something of a form, say, k going from one up to n,
and wecan consider how ever many of them we want.
A sub k, sine of two pi k times t plus 每
that＊s modifying the frequency 每 plus fe sub k 每
allowing myself to modify the phase. Fesub k.
That＊s about the most general kind of sum that we can form out of just the sines or每
and I can do the same thing with cosines,
or I can combine the two and I＊ll say moreabout that in just a second.
All right. So again, many frequencies, one period.
All right.the lowest 每
the longest period in the sum is when k is equal to one,
period one. Thehigher terms, they＊re called harmonics,
because of the connection with music, and it＊sdiscussed in the notes,
because they model 每
because simple sines and cosine modelmusical phenomena as a repeating pattern 每
musical notes. The higher harmonics, thehigher terms,
have higher frequencies, have shorter periods,
but the sum has period onebecause the whole pattern can＊t repeat until the longest period repeats.
All right. Until thelongest pattern is completed.
Now,
I＊m actually gonna post on the website 每
I＊m going togive you a little MATLAB program that allows you to experiment with just these sorts ofsums.
All right. That is, you choose n 每 it forms sums exactly like this 每
you can choosethe a＊s, the amplitudes, you can choose the phases,
and it will plot what a sum looks like.All right.
It＊s called 每
so I have MATLAB program with a graphical user interface.
Iwrote this myself, actually, a couple years ago.
I was very 每 it was the first I ever did inMATLAB,
it was pretty clunky, let me tell ya. But last year,
a student in the class, in 261,took it upon herself to modify it,
which caused me to bump up her grade in the end,
andit＊s really quite a nice little program.
It＊s not complicated,
but it＊ll show you howcomplicated these sums can be.
All right. So there＊s a MATLAB program, which I＊ll poston the website,
sine sum 每
actually it＊s called sine sum two because sine sum one was myown version,
which is now on the ash heap of history.
All right. To plot these sums 每 andit＊s really quite 每
I mean it＊s 每 talk about fun, you know 每
I mean to see how complicateda pattern you can build up out of relatively simple building blocks like this,
it＊s reallypretty good. So we may even 每
we＊re actually trying to see if we can do a homeworkassignment based on this 每
based on the program.
There＊s a feature in the program thatallows you too actually to play the sound that＊s associated with this.
That is,
if youconsider these things as modeling 每
if you consider the simple sinusoids as modeling apure musical note,
then a combination models a combination of musical notes,
and if youput a little button, it plays sound,
you＊ll get something that may sound good or may notsound good.
But it＊s interesting to try. Unfortunately,
the play sound feature doesn＊t seemto work on the Mac,
it only seems to work on Windows.
It requires Windows MediaPlayer or something like that;
Bill Gates＊ version of death 4.2 or something,
I don＊tknow. Anyway,
so we have to see if we can fix it to work on the Mac,
but 每
everythingworks on the Mac fine except for playing the note.
So I＊ll put that up on the web in a zipfile,
and you should fool around with it a little bit.
Okay?
Because it＊ll give you a goodsense of just how complicated these things can be.
All right. Now, so how complicatedcan they be?
That＊s the question that I really wanna address.
I mean,
this sum is alreadymore complicated than just the sine and the cosine alone,
but it doesn＊t begin to exhaustthe possibilities that we want to be able to deal with.
Let me say, to advance thediscussion, actually,
and to really get to the point where I can ask the question in areasonable way,
how general a periodic phenomena can we expect to model with sumslike this.
Let me say a little bit about the different forms that you can write the sum inbecause algebraically 每
for algebraic reasons, primarily algebraic reasons,
there are moreor less convenient ways to write this sum.
Okay.
And I think it＊s worth commentingabout it,
just a little bit. So different ways of writing the sum 每
this sort of sum 每 k equalsone to n of a sub 每
I＊m gonna use a capital in here 每 [inaudible] 每
a sub k sine of two pi kt plus fe sub k.
All right. Now, you can lose the phase, so to speak,
and bring in 每 write itin terms of sines and cosines,
if you use the addition formula for the sine function.
That isthe 每
the formula for the sine of the sum of two angles.
So if you write sine of two pi k tplus fe k as the sine of two pi k t times the cosine of fe k plus the cosine of two pi k ttimes the sine of fe k,
just using the addition formula,
than that sum can be written interms of sines and cosines.
You can write the sum in the form 每 let me use 每
for differentcoefficients, say sum from k equals one to n,
little a k times the cosine of two pi k t,
pluslittle b sub k times the sine of two pi k t.
All right. And you know where the 每
how thelittle ak＊s and the bk＊s are related to the capital A＊s in the phase just by working it out.
All right. So capital A sub k times this thing,
and then there＊s a term coming from thephase 每
you haven＊t lost information about the phase in some sense,
it＊s still there,
butit＊s represented differently in terms of the coefficients out in the form of the sum.
Allright.
This is a very common way of writing these sorts of trigonometric sums.
As amatter of fact, I＊d say it＊s more common in 每
if you look in the applications, even if youlook in the textbooks,
it＊s more common to write the sum this form than it is to write it inthis form.
But there equivalent, all right?
You can go back and for the between the two.
And you can also allow for a constant term,
you can shift the whole thing up.
And that＊salso usually done for purposes of generality.
All right. You can add a constant term.
Andit＊s usually written in the form a zero over two,
the reason why a zero over two is in thereis because of yet,
another form of writing it. Let me just write out the rest of it:
a zeroover two plus, again, sum from n equals 每
for k equals one to n to n of a sub k, cosine oftwo pi k t plus b sub k,
sine of two pi k t. All right.
And electrical engineers always callthis the dc component.
I hate that. All right. But they always do.
All right.
Who alllearned to call this the dc component?
Yeah, I hate that. Not everybody, I＊m glad to seethat.
That＊s because you think of a periodic phenomena,
you think about alternative 每 Idon＊t know what you think about.
You think about alternating current or voltagesomehow is a periodic part,
but then there＊s a direct part that doesn＊t alternate.
There＊s adc part 每 direct current part 每
that doesn＊t alternate, and that＊s that term.
The reason whyI don＊t like calling this the dc component is because what if a problem had absolutelynothing to do with current,
you know?
You＊re sometimes trapped by your language,
andthe field again, as I will say over and over again,
is so broad and so diverse that you don＊twant to trap yourself into thinking about it in only one way.
You know.
You may bemodeling some very complicated phenomena,
and you say, ＆What is a dc component?＊ Issomebody gonna look at you,
like, ＆What are you talking about?＊ You know?
All right.Now,
so that＊s a very common way of writing the form of the sum,
but by far, the mostconvenient way algebraically,
and really in many ways, conceptually,
is to use complexexponentials to write the sum,
not the real sines and cosines. By far.
And this is prettymuch the last time I＊m gonna use sines and cosines.
Or pretty much the last time I＊mgonna write the expression like this,
so it＊s by far better. And I＊ll have to convince you ofthis.
All right. Primarily, algebraically, but also conceptually,
is by far better to use torepresent sine and cosine via complex exponentials.
And write the sum that way. Allright. so what do I mean by that?
Let me just remind you, of course, in either the two pi in t,
[inaudible] formula is cosine of two pi n t plus or k 每
or I guess I＊m calling it k,
letme stick with the terminology there 每
two pi k t plus sine of two pi k plus i times the sineof two pi k t.
Oh, yes, that＊s something else. All right.
I＊m gonna announce a declarationof principle.
I is the square root of minus one, in this class.
Not j. Deal with it. Get over it.All right.
For me, for this class, it＊s i. You can use j if you want.
I will use i. Now,because of Oiler＊s formula 每
Oiler＊s famous formula 每
you can express sines and cosinesin terms of the completive exponential ant it＊s conjugate,
that is, very simple formula,
thecosine is the real part and the sine is the imaginary part.
So cosine of two pi k t is then eto the pi i is the real part.
Two pi i k t plus e to the minus two pi i k t over two.
And thesine of two pi k t, likewise,
is the imaginary part that＊s e to the two pi i k t minus e to theminus two pi i k t divided by two i.
There is an appendix in the notes on the algebra ofcomplex numbers,
so if you＊re at all rusty on that, you should review that.
All right.
Because you＊re gonna want to be able to manipulate complex numbers,
and I＊m thinkingprimarily here in terms of working with complex conjugates with real parts andimaginary parts.
You＊re gonna wanna be able to do that with confidence and gusto.
Allright.
So if you＊re at all rusty in manipulating complex number 每
and complexexponentials, look over the chapter.
All right? Matter of fact, on the first problem set,
there are several problems that you give you practice in exactly this and manipulatingcomplex numbers.
All right. Complex exponentials. Now, because of this 每
and I won＊t 每I won＊t write it out in detail,
you can obviously then convert a sum which is not gone,
which looks in terms of sines and cosines 每
in terms of complex exponentials.
So you canconvert a trigonometric sum as before to the form sum 每
and I＊ll write it like this 每 sumfrom k equals minus n to n,
so it includes the zeros term, the constant term,
c sub k 每 e tothe two pi i k t. All right.
We are now 每 the C sub k＊s are complex numbers.
Everythingin sight is complex. So, All right.
The c k＊s are complex. Now, they can be 每
all right 每they can be expressed 每 I won＊t do this and 每
I was gonna give you a homework problemon this,
but I decided not to. You can do this just for fun.
You can see how the differentcoefficients are related.
So start with the expression in terms of sines and cosines,
makethe substitution in terms of the complex exponential and see what happens to thecoefficients.
All right. You will find, actually, a very important symmetry property.
Allright. These are complex numbers,
but they＊re not just arbitrary complex numbers,
theysatisfy symmetry property.
And it＊s because of the symmetry that the total sum is real.
All right. The symmetry property 每 this comes up a lot 每
and we＊ll see similar sort ofthings reflected actually,
when we talked about Fourier transforms.
That is c sub 每 thesum goes from minus n up to n 每
they satisfy the property,
the c sub minus k is c sub kcomplex conjugate,
c k bar. All right.
That＊s a very important identity that＊s satisfied bythe coefficients for a real signal like that,
and it comes up often. All right.
it＊s one of thethings you have to keep in mind.
All right.
That＊s a consequence of actually making theconversion.
That is,
starting with a formula in terms of sines and cosines,
and then gettingthe formula in terms of the complex numbers.
All right. Conversely, conversely, if youstart with the sum of this form,
all right,
where the coefficient satisfies the symmetryproperty,
then the total some will be real.
That＊s because you can group a positive termand a negative term,
and because of this relationship here,
you＊ll be adding a complexnumber plus its conjugate,
so you＊ll get a real 每 results out of that.
All right. So if thecoefficients satisfy this,
then the signal is real. And conversely,
if the signal is real andyou write it like that,
then the coefficients have to satisfy the symmetry property.
Yeah?Student:What is that 每 [inaudible] 每
Instructor (Brad Osgood):What is that line?
That line is 每 indicates complex conjugate.
All right. So for a general 每 all right, do I have to say anymore first?
So for generalcomplex number a plus b i,
the conjugate is a minus b i. Okay.
There are differentnotations for complex conjugates,
sometimes some people use different 每 some peopleuse an asterisk,
a star, some people even use a dagger. All right.
But I think by far 每 it＊strue, I＊m not making that up.
But this is the most common notation. All right.
And that isanother notation I will use.Okay.
Now, now, now, now. We are ready, at last,
to at least ask the question that＊s reallyat the heart of all of this.
How general can this be? How general can this be?
I mean, I＊min the form now, algebraically 每
well,
I＊m in the form now where I can ask the question,
and as we＊ll see algebraically,
writing sums of this form is by far the easiest way toapproach it.
So we can now ask the fundamental question.
Why is there something rather thannothing?
Let＊s kick that one around for awhile. The fundamental question 每
so again,
f oft is a periodic function of period one.
All right. Can we write it, f of t and that sort ofsum,
k going from minus n to n of c sub k e to the two pi i k t.
So again,
I＊m assuming thesignal is real here so the coefficient satisfies symmetry relation;
just keep your eye on theball here.The fundamental question is this.
You have a general periodic function, can you write itas a trigonometric sum?
Can you express it in terms of sines and cosines?
Can youexpress it in terms of the fundamental building blocks?
All right. By the way, linearity isplaying a role here,
although again, I haven＊t said it explicitly until now,
we＊reconsidering linear combinations of the basic building blocks.
We＊re considering a linearway of combining the basic trigonometric functions,
the basic periodic functions. Allright. A linear way of doing that.
So that＊s the fundamental question. And the answer 每
I＊ll tell you next time.
But youdon＊t think I＊d make such a big deal out of it if the answer was no.
So 每 but there＊s a lotto do. And answering this question 每
answering this question led to a lot of very profoundand far-
reaching investigations.All right. Now 每 but I want to get started on it.
All right. Now, let me give you a littleclue.
Yeah 每Student:
[Inaudible] earlier you were starting with one.
Instructor (Brad Osgood):Pardon? Why am I not starting with one?
Well, for one thing每
so the question is why does the sum go from minus n to n,
and why doesn＊t it just gofrom one to n?
Well, for one thing, if it went from one to n,
the signal wouldn＊t be real, right?
Remember there＊s this combination of the positive terms and the negative terms,
allright?
And the positive terms and the negative terms 每
because of the symmetry relationof the coefficient,
the positive and the negative terms combine to give you a real signal 每
to give you a real part.
And it＊s a fact that if you start with a real signal in terms of sinesand cosines,
and then you use complex exponentials to express it this way,
you will findthat it＊s the symmetric sum.
It goes from minus n to n. Okay.By the way,
I should have said something over here, I suppose.
Note one thing, by theway, that c sub-zero is equal to c sub-
minus zero. Zero being what it is. C sub minus zerois equal to c sub-
zero is equal to c zero bar.
What does it mean to say that a complexnumber is equal to its conjugate?
Student:It is real.Instructor (Brad Osgood):
It＊s real. All right.
So the one coefficient that you know forsure is real,
others may be real, it may just work out that way,
but the one coefficient thatyou know is real for sure,
is the zero of coefficient. All right. so it must be real.
So c zerois real. That＊s just a little aside,
c zero is real.All right. You have to be a little 每
you have to cut me a little slack here. Like I said,
weall have to cut each other a little slack.
There＊s so many little bits, you know, to observe 每
little pieces, little comments and things like that.
I can＊t make all of them, all right? Ihope I put all of them,
or most of them, in the lecture notes, all right,
in the notes so yousee these things. But,
as I say,
there＊s so many things along the way that you could pointout,
that you can note,
that we just can＊t do it all because I want to keep my eye on thebigger picture.
All right.
But this is one thing that comes up often enough.
So there＊ll be,you know,
there＊ll be instances where you have to read the 每
read the notes carefully andtry to make note of all those things.
And it＊s hard. It＊s hard. You know,
it＊s hard to knowwhen you＊re gonna need this little fact or that little fact because there＊s so many littlefacts.
But you＊ll see when the whole thing 每 when you 每
if you keep the big picture in mind,
inmany cases the details will take care of themselves.
Really. Now, where was I?Yes? A secret of the universe.
All right.
Here＊s a pretty big secret of the universe,
actually, coming your way. When you try to apply 每
when you＊re trying to see howmathematics works,
and when you try to apply mathematics to various problems,
youoften have a question like this. What if 每
how can 每 what 每 how can something happen?
All right.
Is it possible to write something like this?
All right. Now, a very good firstapproach 每
and I＊m serious about this.
When you＊re doing your own work and you＊retrying to look at a mathematical model of something,
you say, can I do something likethis?
Often the first step is to suppose that you can,
and see what the consequences are.All right.
Then later on, you can say, all right,
then maybe I should try this because thatseems to be what has to happen.
All right. And then you go backwards. All right.
Andmathematicians will never tell you this because they like to sort of cover their tracks.
They say, ＆Well, it obviously goes like this,
＊ you know, and,
＆We＊re obviously going todefine this formula and that formula,
and life is going to work out so simply.
＊ But whatthey don＊t show you is often that first step of saying,
suppose the problem is solved, whathas to happen?
All right. So suppose you can do this.
We can write f of t equals the sumfrom k equals minus n to n,
c sub-k e to the two pi i k t. What has to happen?
All right.Now, by that I mean, if you can write this,
what are the coefficients? If you can write anequation like this,
then what I＊m asking here is,
what are the mystery coefficients interms of f?
Coefficient c sub-k in terms of f 每 f is given to you.
All right.
So theunknowns in this expression are the coefficients.
And the question is, can you solve forthem?
All right. Suppose you can write it like that.
Can you solve for the coefficients?Can we solve for the c k?
All right. I＊m gonna take a very na.ve approach.
All right. I＊mgonna isolate it. What do you?
It＊s like an algebraic equation. To start with an algebraicequation,
isolate the unknown. So isolate, like, the,
I don＊t know, Mth coefficient orsomething like that.
All right. So isolate c m out of this. That is 每
it＊s a big old sum,right? So f of t is, you know,
all these terms plus c sub m e to the two pi i m t plus all therest of the terms.
That is to say, I can write c sub-m e to the two pi i m t,
is f of t minus allthe terms that don＊t involve m,
so let me write it like this. Say, sum over k different fromm of c sub-
k e to the two pi i k t. All right.
I haven＊t done anything except algebraicallymanipulated the equation to bring the one mystery term,
or one fixed term on the otherside. All right.
All I did here 每 so f of t is this big sum.
One of those terms in the sum is csub m e to the two pi i m t 每
I wanna solve for the unknowns. All right.
So solve for theunknowns one unknown at a time.
So this is the Mth term in the sum,
bring that over tothe other side of the equation,
write c sub m e to the two pi i m t is f of t minus all theterms that don＊t involve m.
Okay. And then, write that as 每 that＊s almost isolating c sub-
m,
and not quite because it＊s got a complex exponential in front of it.
So multiply bothsides 每 this board is not so great 每
multiply both sides by e to the minus two pi i m t.
So csub-
m is e to the minus two pi i m t times f of t minus the sum over all k different from mof c sub-
k e to the minus two pi i m t times e to the two pi i k t.
You with me? Nothing onmy sleeve. All right.
All right. Now, that＊s brilliant.
I have isolated one unknown in termsof all the other unknowns.
All right. So,
I don＊t know if one can say that we have reallymade progress here.
So we need another idea. This is as far as algebra can take you.
Allright. Algebra says, you wanna solve for the unknown,
fine. Isolate, you know,
what didyour eighth grade teacher tell you?
Put the one unknown on one side of the equation,
puteverything else on the other side of the equation.
Hope and pray. All right.
So we put theone unknown on one side of the equation,
everything else is on the other side of theequation.
Hope and pray. Now,
the desperate mathematician at this point looking forsomething to do.
Let me actually take this out one more algebraic step.
Let me justcombine those two exponentials there,
and write this as c sub-
m is e to the minus two pi im t minus the sum over all terms different from m of c sub-
k e to the two pi i 每 two pi i kminus m times t.
I＊m just combining the two complex exponentials there.
All right. Great.Student:[Inaudible]Instructor (Brad Osgood):
What?Student:F of t.Instructor (Brad Osgood):
F of t. Picky, picky. All right. F of t minus.
All right. Now,good. So now, they say that we need another idea.
And the desperate mathematician atthis moment will think of one or two things 每
one of two things.
[Inaudible] theydifferentiate or integrate.
I mean, what＊s beyond algebra? Calculus.
What＊s in calculus?Derivatives and intervals.
All right. So, here＊s a clue. Derivatives won＊t work,
butintervals will.All right. We need another idea.
And that＊s a good idea, it＊s an inspired idea.
But[inaudible] because it works, and I＊ll show you way.
So I＊m gonna integrate both sidesfrom zero to one over one period.
All right.
All I have to worry about here is one period.
Everything＊s periodic at period one, so I integrate over 每
I integrate from zero to one.What if I do 每
what do I get?Well, certainly, if I integrate zero to one of c sub-
m d t, that just gives me c sub-m. Allright.
So what about the rest of it? So I get 每
I get c sub-
m is equal to the interval fromzero to one,
e to the minus two pi i m t, f of t d t,
minus the interval of the sum is the sumof the interval 每
let me write this, sum from all the different 每
all the terms k different m每 and the constant comes out 每
c sub-k, the interval from zero to one, e to the two pi i kminus m 每
k minus m 每 t d t. That＊s a t there. T. Ouch.
All right.
I＊ve integrated both sides from zero to one.
All right. Now, watch this. Allright. Watch.
I can integrate that complex exponential,
that＊s a simple function.
I canintegrate that just like I integrated in calculus.
All right. The interval from zero to one,
eto the two pi i k minus m t d t. Now, k is different from m.
All right. If k is equal to m,I＊m just e to the zero here,
I just get one [inaudible] so the k is different from m.
So theinterval of this is one over two pi i 每
trust me 每
integrating this is the same as integratingan ordinary function 每
two pi i, as you did in calculus.
One over two pi i k minus m e to the two pi i k minus m t,
evaluated from t going fromzero to one. Straightforward integration.
Straightforward integration, which is equal to 每
we are almost done. We are almost there.One over two pi i k minus m,
that makes sense, right? Because k is different from m,
soit＊s not a problem. E to the two pi i k minus m times one 每
so that＊s e to the pi i k minusm minus e to the zero.
All right. But either the two pi i k minus m,
that＊s e to the two pi itimes an integer.
That＊s like sine of two pi times an integer,
cosine of two pi times aninteger 每 that＊s one.
And e to the zero is also better known as one.
So this is better knownas one minus one,
which is better known as zero.Nothing. All this crap integrates zero.
Excuse me. All right. Incredible. What is theupshot?
It all goes away. What is the upshot? The upshot is,
that c sub-m 每 what＊s left?What＊s left is c sub-
m is the interval from zero to one 每 that 每
all that 每 all the terms ofthe sum here are gone 每
are gone. They integrated out to zero.
What remains is theinterval from zero to one of e to the minus two pi i m t f of t d t.
All right. Now, in principle,
this is known because you start out by assuming you knew f.
Suppose I know f, what has to happen? All right.
Well, suppose I＊m given f, and I write fas this sum,
what has to happen? Here is the answer. All right.
Here is the answer. Let mesummarize.We have solved for the unknowns.
All right. So given f of t 每 periodic of period one 每
suppose we can write f of t as the sum,
k equals minus n to n of c k e to the two pi i k t.
What has to happen?
What has to happen is the coefficients have to be given by thisformula.
Then you must have 每 I＊ll just write c sub-
k instead of c sub-m 每
[inaudible] ofthe k of coefficient is the interval from zero to one of e to the minus two pi i k t f of t d t.
That＊s what has to happen. All right.
It＊s an important first step in applying mathematics to any given problem,
whether it＊s amathematical problem or a non-
mathematical problem. Suppose the problem is solved,
what has to happen? If the problem is solved,
mean,
suppose you have this representationthen the coefficients have to be given by this formula.
All right. So next time, I＊m gonna turn this around saying,
suppose we give thesecoefficients by the formula,
do we have something like that, and in what sense?
And thatwill lead us to great things.All right.
So more on that next time.[End of Audio]Duration: