TheFourierTransformAndItsApplications-Lecture03All right?
Okay.
Let me remind youwhere we finished up last time.
We took an important first step in understanding theanalysis
and undertaking the analysis of periodic phenomena
and trying to represent ageneral periodic phenomena
by the sum of much simpler periodic phenomena under thisis complex exponential?
So think in terms of sines and cosines, all right?
So last time,
I say we took the first step in analyzing general periodic phenomena via thesum,
so several combination,
a linear combination of simple building blocks,
simpleperiodic phenomena.
So let me remind you what we did because it＊s very important that
you realize what we did and what we didn＊t do.
We said suppose that you can write aperiodic signal in a certain form what has to happen.
So we start off by saying F of T is agiven periodic function,
periodic signal. Function, signal same thing.
And just to bedefinite we took it to have period one,
all right?
And the question is can it be representedin terms of others
and suppose it can be represented in terms of other simple signals ofperiod one,
namely the complex exponential.So suppose we can write F of T as a sum,
say something like this. Okay? K from minus Nto N,
cease of K, E to the two pi I, KT. There was a question,
by the way, somebody sentme an e-
mail about why the sum is symmetric and so why does it go from minus N to N
and we talked a little bit about this last time.
This is also discussed a little bit more in thenotes.
You can think in terms of sines and cosines,
all right?
And the idea is that if youhave a real signal the coefficient [inaudible],
but it bears repeating.
The coefficientsatisfying an important symmetry relationship.
The complex numbers they cease ofminus K is equal to cease of K bar and
because of that the positive frequencies combineswith the negative frequencies.
The positive terms combine with the negative terms to giveyou a real part.
So will give you essentially a sum of cosines.
Okay?
Or sum of sines and cosines because the values are complex.
And it＊s a symmetric sum.
Instead of going from one to N or zero to N,
if you use complex exponentials it goes fromminus N to N.
The proof of the helpfulness of this representation will just becomeapparent as we use it,
all right? As I said before,
the algebraic work in the analysis is justmade incomparably easier
by using complex exponentials than real sines and cosine＊.
Just the calculations become that much easier.
All right.So, once again, suppose we can do this.
Then what we found is the coefficients had to begiven by a certain formula.
So then the coefficients are given by C sub-
K is the intervalfrom zero to one, E to the minus two pi I,
KT times F of T, DT, all right?
It＊s an explicitformula for the coefficients.
And in principle that＊s known, all right?
If you know thefunction then you can carry out the integration in principle.
And I want to remind youthat this formula 每
there were two parts of deriving that formula.
There was a sort ofalgebraic part,
where we just try to isolate the K coefficient and that certain way,
but thenthe analytic part invoked a little calculus
where to solve for the coefficient I had tointegrate.
This depended on a very important relationship of the complex exponentials.
This I＊ll write over here 每 oh, right here.
The interval from 每 I＊ll write it over here.
The interval from zero to one, E to the,
say,two pi I, NT, E to the two pi minus two pi I,
MT, DT.
So that＊s interval from zero to oneif I combine the two ended up two pi I and minus MT,
DT. That＊s either one if M is equalto N.
So in that case I＊m just integrating to the zero,
I＊m just integrating one.
Where it＊sequal to zero if M is different from N,
all right? Fundamental relationship.
We＊ll see thatmaking its triumphant return a little later on.
All right.Now,
that＊s fine and that was a very important first step,
but it was only the first step.
Thesecond step is to turn the question around,
all right?
The first step says suppose we canwrite the function in this form,
then the coefficients have to be given by this formula.
Thesecond step is to turn that around and ask the following:
When is that really possible? SoI want to turn this around.
So, again,
you＊re given F of T periodic of period one,
all right?I know what the answer has to be,
all right? In a sense, I know what the coefficients haveto be.
They have to be given by this, so I＊m gonna define them,
all right?Define 每 and I want to use a different notation.
I want to introduce a different notationthat＊s quite standard in this subject.
Define F hat of K to be this interval.
The intervalfrom zero to one of E to the minus two pi I,
KT, F of T, DT. So, again, in principle youcan compute this,
all right? You＊re given F.
You can carry out the integration of F againstthis complex exponential.
And it＊s often then by F hat K and this is called the K three Acoefficient of F.
What did we say? K four A coefficient, all right?
So it depends on F and,in fact, it can viewed as a transform of F,
although we won＊t use that terminology 每
well,
I won＊t stress that terminology quite so much now
because it will become much moreuseful when we talk about the Fourier transform.
It＊s not the Fourier transform. This isthe Fourier coefficient.
So it＊s a transform of F, but evaluated on the integers.
For each K,
I have a correspondingnumber F hat of K given by this interval.
And the question is, do we have 每 can we writethe function?
Can we sit beside the function in terms of its Fourier coefficients?
Can wewrite F of T is the sum K equals minus N to N,
F hat of K, E to the two pi I, KT for sumN?
Is there some sum of these things
that will allow us to express the given periodicfunction in terms of these simple building blocks?
That＊s the question. I say,
I know whatthe answer has to be if we can do it.
The answer has to be given 每 such an expression hasto involve this.
That＊s what I talked about last time. The question is does it really work?
If it does,
if a statement like this is true you have to believe that it gives you incrediblepower because,
again,
a general periodic function can be decomposed in this way intovery simple terms.
Analyzing a very complex system of periodic inputs,
periodic outputsmight be possible to do by analyzing what the system does
to the relatively simple inputsand outputs given by the complex exponentials,
all right? So if so we can analyzecomplex systems,
simple building blocks. Not a great sentence here,
but you get what Imean. Simple components,
simple building blocks. I＊d like another try at that sentence,
but I think I＊d just rather leave it there,
all right? Okay.Now,
this method is only gonna be really helpful if it＊s fairly general.
And that＊s alwaysbeen the question I＊ve raised a couple times.
How general really is this?
How general canwe expect this to be if it works?
All right.
Is it worth putting the time and effort into evenaddressing this question
if it＊s only gonna work in a few specialized cases
that somehowwe can handle an ad hoc basis when they came up.
Well, let me give you a little warninghere,
all right? Let me show you the kind of things,
not to be negative about it,
but let meshow you how high the stakes are,
all right? This is a very high stakes question.
And letme do that by a couple of examples,
all right?
Examples that are natural enough they can come up fairly easily in applications.
Let＊slook at some examples of some of the kind of signals that could come up.
For example,
you could take a signal that looks like this,
all right? I＊ll draw it over here. I＊ll just drawthe graph.
Something that looks like this.
It could model a switch that＊s periodically on oroff,
zero or one, current is flowing or it＊s not flowing.
So something like it＊s one for halfa second and then zero for half a second,
all right?
That＊s the basic period and then itrepeats.
So one down to zero. One-half and then it repeats and it goes up,
then it＊s on,then it＊s off, then it＊s on,
then it＊s off, and so on and so on. Okay?
So one, three halves,two, and so on and so on,
all right?
That＊s a periodic function and it repeats also for thenegative numbers.
That＊s a periodic function of period one,
all right? So switch on forhalf a second,
off for half a second and repeats. All right.
Can we expect to write, let＊scall this F of T,
all right? There＊s the graph,
and I can write down the formula for it.
Canwe write F in the form? I can compute the coefficients.
I won＊t do it, but, in fact,
thecoefficients are calculated in the notes,
all right? You can carry out the integration.
It＊snot a complicated interval to carry out.
You＊re just integrating the function one over theinterval from zero to a half.
That＊s all of the function times a complex exponential.
Soyou can compute easily F hat of K. F hat of K would be,
in this case, the interval fromzero to a half.
Let＊s say, I won＊t carry it out. E to the minus two pi I,
KT times one DT,all right?
It＊s one on the interval from zero to a half and zero on the interval from one-
half to one.
You only compute it on the interval on one period,
on the interval from zeroto one-
half and that＊s an easy interval to figure out.
And we write F of T is sum from Kequals N to N,
F hat of K, E to the two pi I, KT. That＊s the question.
And the answer is,no or at least not with a finite sum.
But I hate to build up all this drama asking thisfundamental question only
to answer it no for a relatively simple example.
So the answeris no, not for a finite sum.
Why?
Because the complex exponentials thinking they＊re justsines and cosines,
all right? They＊re continuous.
And the sum of a finite number ofcontinuous functions is continuous.
It can＊t possibly represent a discontinuousphenomenon.
You can＊t represent a discontinuous phenomenon by a continuousphenomenon,
all right?
You learned that theorem back in calculus,
you know.
Some jerkof a math teacher probably said something like and the sum of two continuous functions,
of course, is continuous. And you said, yeah,
right. Okay, fine. What＊s the point? Well,
here＊s the point right now for the first time.
This limits what you can do. It limits whatyou might want to do.
You can＊t represent a discontinuous function by the sum of a finitenumber of continuous functions.
Bad luck, all right? Well,
what if a function iscontinuous at least,
all right? But maybe has a corner. So let＊s look at the secondexample.
Let＊s say a triangle wave. Something that looks like this.
Up, down, up, down,up, down, and so on. So on an interval from zero to one.
So it＊s periodic of period oneand, again,
the power of these,
along the negative axis also are for negative values of T.
So, again,
we can easily compute the Fourier coefficients.
That＊s not a problem. Theyexist.
It＊s not a problem to carry out the integration and,
again, that＊s done.
I think it＊sworked out in the notes explicitly and if not it＊s easy enough to do.
I will not do it inpublic. Again,
you can compute the Fourier coefficients.
Has to be integrated in twopieces. Has to be integrated.
The interval from zero to a half of the function T times thecomplex exponential plus the interval from one-
half to one of the function of whateverthis is on the corresponding interval times the other times the complex interval.
But youcan do it, all right? It requires a little bit of work,
but it＊s not hard. You can do it.Can we write,
I＊ll call this F of T, again.
My generic error function is always called F,
Fof T. Can we write, again, the corresponding sum?
Sum K equals minus N to N, E to theF head of K,
E to the two pi I KAT. And, again, the answer is no.
Not for a finite sum.Why? Well,
because it＊s your jerk of a calculus teacher probably told you
if your twofunctions are differentiable then the sum of two functions is differentiable.
And you said,fine, fine, whatever.
And it didn＊t seem to matter at the time,
but now it matters becausethis function is not differentiable.
It has a corner, all right?
But the complex exponentialsare just sines and cosines.
They are differentiable. Their sum is differentiable.
You can＊trepresent a non-
differentiable function as a finite sum of differential functions.
It won＊twork. You just can＊t do it. The right-
hand side is differentiable. The left-hand side is notdifferentiable.
Okay? Now,
we could go on like this with more and more bad news,
allright? That is, if there is a discontinuity in 每
so here＊s the discontinuity in the firstderivative,
all right? There＊s a corner here.
We could draw examples that would looksmoother,
but we could draw examples where there＊s this continuity in the second
derivative or maybe the first and second derivatives are fine,
but there＊s discontinuity inthe third derivative and so on and so on.
If there is any lack of smoothness, if there is anycorner,
no matter how smooth that corner looks,
if there is some discontinuity in somehigh derivative you＊re screwed,
to use a technical term. All right?
Any discontinuity in any derivative includes writing F of T is this sum.
Sum from Kequals minus N to N minus N to N of F hat A,
E to the two pi I,
KT for a finite sumbecause these functions are infinitely differentiable.
These functions are as smooth asthey can be.
They＊re sines and cosines.
And you can＊t take the sum of those sines andcosines and put them together
and get something that＊s not infinitely differentiable,
allright? So this great idea 每
we might as well quit now or take the rest of the quarter off.
Because it doesn＊t look very general at all.
I mean,
the kind of signals you come upagainst may have jumps,
may have corners, may have discontinuities,
whatever. All right.
Maybe we want to make an approximation that they＊re as smooth as can be and then wecan use this.
And it＊s an argument,
but it＊s getting away from what we really hope toaccomplish here.
Let me, before I go any further,
say that there＊s a maxim lurking here that＊s important,
allright? That is,
if we can＊t represent it as a finite sum
then we have to turn to infinite sumsor at least larger and larger finite sums.
Sums of more and more terms. And the maximthat＊s lurking,
and I＊ll say it now and then we＊ll go back to the general discussion,
is thatit takes high frequencies to make sharp corners,
or any corners for that matter.
Maxim isit takes high frequencies to make sharp corners or really any kind of,
it sounds better ifyou say it like this,
but really any kind of corner, all right?
Any time there＊s some kind ofdiscontinuity in some high derivative,
that means that you＊re gonna have troublerepresenting that phenomenon as a finite sum.
You＊re gonna have to take N larger andlarger to try to represent it more and more accurately.
It takes more and more terms,
takeshigher and higher frequencies to make that bend,
all right?
Even for a relatively highdegree of smoothness.
All right? Now, by the way, you may think,
again, that his is anartificial maxim that is,
real signals don＊t have sharp corners, but that＊s not true.
I mean,all the time when you, and later when we talk about filtering,
producing sharp corners assharp as you can is actually an important part of signal processing.
Sometimes you wantto take a signal and cut off after a certain point.
Either cut it off in time or cut it off infrequency.
Some of you, I＊m sure, have had some experience with this,
all right?
Sometimes your signal starts out pretty smooth,
but for other reasons you want to make itsomehow less smooth.
You want to cut things off and cutting things off can introduce
high frequencies in trying to represent the signal
that is something else that has to be dealtwith,
all right?
So there are some very tricky and very practical questions that go alongwith this maxim.
All right. Now, like I said,
at this point you say well what＊s happened tothis grand general program that you＊ve been announcing?
If it＊s not gonna work and if Ican＊t consider finite sums to represent all but the most specialized phenomena,
if there＊sany sum slight discontinuity in there at any level of smoothness,
then what good is any ofthis?
And the come back to that is we have to consider infinite sums,
all right?
To represent the general periodic phenomena,
periodic signals we have to considerinfinite sums,
all right? That＊s a mathematical point. As a practical matter,
of course, youcan＊t sum up an infinite series.
You can only sum up an approximation,
but if you want tohave some confidence in what you＊re doing and
if you want to know what errors youmight have to analyze,
the first thing you have to do is realize that you have to expandyour purview from finite sums to infinite sums.
So to represent a more general periodicphenomena we must consider infinite sums of the form,
say,
for minus infinity to infinityhalf hat of K,
E to the two pi I, KT.
It may and be that not all these coefficients are nonzero.
Some of them may be zero and so on,
but for sure if the function has any sort ofdiscontinuity at any level of derivatives
then these coefficients are gonna go out andyou＊re gonna have non-
zero coefficients as far as you go out, all right?
Any non-
smooth phenomenon signal will generate infinitely many,
not just a finitelymany,
but infinitely many Fourier coefficients,
all right?
The only way you couldpossibly have a finite Fourier series is if the function you start out with were infinitelysmooth,
all right? Now, that＊s a problem, all right?
I just want to say the stakes are highhere because if you＊re gonna deal with an infinite sum mathematically,
and even forapplications,
you have to talk about issues of convergence,
all right? How accurate is thisgonna be?
If I cut it off after a finite number of terms,
how accurate is it gonna be? Allright?
If the series is converging and I cut it off after a finite number of terms maybe I
have a certain amount of confidence that I＊m getting a pretty good approximation to myfunction,
all right?
But if the series is not converging and I still try to cut it off after a finite number of terms,
what confidence do I have that I＊m taking a reasonable approximation to the signal that Ireally want?
So you have to deal with issues of convergence.
You are forced to if youwant this theory to apply at all generally.
Okay? And, again, not just for mathematicalreasons,
but also for practical reasons. Now, that＊s hard,
all right?
There are a lot of veryhard questions here and we＊re not gonna go into the mathematical analysis of all of them.
I do want to give you a big picture.
I want to give you some good news and some hardnews,
but ultimately pretty good news,
about how this is dealt with because it has all beensorted out.
But it took generations of mathematicians and scientists and engineersworking
on this to finally resolve all these issues.
Why is this so 每 I mean,
talking about convergence of series is hard anyway.
It＊sparticularly hard in cases like this because the terms are oscillating,
all right? Thecomplex exponential, again,
think in terms of sines and cosines, all right?
If I split this upinto its real and imaginary parts,
sometimes the cosine is positive, sometimes the cosineis negative,
sometimes the sine is positive, sometimes the sine is negative.
So you havepositive terms and negative terms and adding infinitely many of them up,
all right?
Soconvergence for infinite sines like this has to depend on some type of cancellations thatare going.
There has to be some sort of conspiracy that＊s making this series converge fora given value of T,
all right?You need a conspiracy of cancellations,
how about that?
To make such a series convergebecause of the oscillation,
all right? And that＊s hard to study.
That can be hard to study ina given case.
I just want you to be aware of this that the stakes are high and the issues arereal.
Now, here＊s what I want to do. I want to talk about the situation.
I want to give youa number of statements,
theorems that cover what the story is here.
And, again,
we＊re notgoing to go through the proofs of these things.
It＊s not so crucial for us the mathematicaldetails.
A lot of them are covered in the notes, not all of them,
however,
and I＊ll say alittle bit more about that as well.
But I do want you aware of where the hard parts are andwhat the answers are,
all right?So what I want to do is,
I want to have a summary of the main results.
That is theconvergence when the function is continuous,
which happens often enough that you wantto know or,
let me say, smooth.
It has to be an infinite series if it＊s not infinitely smooth,
all right? The convergence, or what passes for convergence,
when you have certaindiscontinuities and here there is a nice and helpful statement about
when you have a jumpdiscontinuity,
all right?
These two cases are actually relatively straightforward.
It＊s easyto remember and it＊s easy to have a certain amount of confidence in what the results are,
again. Although, I won＊t prove it. I won＊t go through the proofs.
And, finally,
the convergence issues in general
and they involve some very really quitedeep changes in the perspective
that you have to adopt toward this circle of problems.
Convergence in general, all right?
You actually do have quite a broad general statementthat covers pretty much all situations
that come up reasonably in practice.
But the notionof convergence is a little bit different
and the mathematics involved in here it took a longtime to sort out,
all right?
So this involves a fundamental change of perspective.
As said, I＊m not gonna do the tails,
but I at least want to say some of the words and I＊lltell you why.
Because it has become so pervasive that is,
it＊s become so 每
the frameworkfor studying convergence in general,
even as it applies maybe to these simple situations,
has become so standard that you will see this in all the literature,
all right?
You＊ll see inthe engineering literature,
the terms that I＊m gonna use orthogonality,
mean squareconvergence, L2, things like that.
I＊ll say all those words and I＊ll tell you what they mean,
but it＊s become absolutely the way of talking about these things.
And if you look atmodern treatments of signal processing,
and I＊m thinking, in particular, here of wavelimit analysis,
which has become very popular in recent years.
You＊ll hear about orthonormal basis for so and so
and distinguish from the complexexponentials as orthonormal basis.
You＊ll hear all the terminology that goes along withthis point of view.
So I think, at least,
I want you to come away from this with someunderstanding
and familiarity with the terminology that goes along with it,
all right?That＊s as far as I want to go with it.
But even that I hope is gonna be helpful for you.
Allright. So let me look at these cases,
because these cases are pretty straightforward andthey＊re good to know.
Convergence when the signal is continuous.
Yes, good news. Itconverges, all right? So that is if 每
so continuous case, all right?So, again,
you can form the Fourier series, all right?
You have that the series sum Kequals minus infinity to infinity,
F hat of K, E to the two pi I,
KT converges for each T tothe value F of T point Y.
Is that means that you plug in a value of T into this sum and addit all up,
then you have a series of constants, and what will it add up to?
It will add up tothe value of the function F of T.
So that＊s good, all right?
If the function＊s continuousthen you know the series is gonna converge
and it＊s gonna give you the right value,
allright? Good. Not so easy to prove, all right?
It takes a little work to prove that and,
again,
that＊s sort of sketched out in the notes,
all right? Not all the details, but a number of them.
You can at least see the broad outlines.
And you will find this discussed in various levelsof abstraction
in most mathematical books on Fourier analysis,
Fourier series, all right?But that＊s what to keep in mind there.
So the continuous case is good. We call this point-
wise convergence, again, because you plug in a value of T,
a point in time, add up theseries,
which is then a sum of constants
and you＊re guaranteed that the sum will convergeto the function F of T.
In the case the function is smooth actually,
you get a little bitmore. If the function is differentiable,
the smooth case.
So that＊s if you have variousdegrees of differentiability.
If it has one derivative, if it has two derivatives,
and thenthere＊s the question about are the derivative＊s continuous and so on,
so I don＊t want tosplit hairs on this. And,
again,
there＊s a fairly precise statement that＊s given in the notes,
but it says this.
So if it＊s smooth and the particulars continuous,
so you know the seriesconverges.So, again,
the series converges, the Fourier series,
K equals minus infinity to infinity Fhat of K,
E to the two pi I, KT converges to F of T.
That＊s the same as in the continuouscase,
but there＊s actually more to it than this that,
again,
can be helpful sometimes ifyou＊re trying to estimate errors.
You actually get what＊s called uniform convergence andwhat that means 每
the way you should think about this is for different values of T
you cancontrol the rate at which the series converges.
Same rate for different values of T. So,
again, without trying to make it 每 I can make this precise,
but I don＊t want to because itrequires too much notation.
So you can i.e. think of it this way, you can control,
or youcan estimate, the rate of convergence,
how fast the series is converging.
Add different values of T depending on the degree of smoothness.
What this often meansis you get estimates on the size of the coefficients,
you get estimates on the differencebetween the function,
and a finite approximation, a finite version of the series,
dependingon the smoothness, all right?
The smooth of the function is the faster it converges.
That＊sone way of looking at it. And, again,
without giving a technical definition of it.
Yeah?Student:[Inaudible]Instructor (Brad Osgood):
Well,
what the uniform convergence means roughly and,
again,
what I don＊t want to write I don＊t want to write a lot of epsilon＊s and N＊s andthings like that,
is if this is the function, all right? All right?
It＊s periodics, or the pattern,repeats.
Then what I mean by uniform convergence is that if you look at a finiteapproximation,
so if you look at a finite version of the sum just going from minus N to N,
then that will track. So this is F of T, all right?
That＊s the original function.
And theapproximation does something like,
you know, it tracks the function along the way.
Thisis [inaudible] sum, all right?
You can estimate uniformly over the interval how far theapproximation is from the function,
all right?
So instead of just saying at a particular point the series is converging,
all right? So, again,
if I pick a particular point here then the value of the approximation
is approaching thevalue of the function.
That＊s fine.
That＊s what happens for the continuous case.
For thesmooth case, you can say more than that.
You can say uniformly how close theapproximation is to the function over the entire interval,
over all from zero to one, allright? And you can give an estimate for that,
all right?
That＊s what the smoothness givesfor you,
all right? And, again, you could write that down precisely,
but I＊m not gonna dothat.
There is actually a statement of this theorem that＊s given in the notes,
if you＊re interested.And it＊s interesting.
I mean, and, again,
it can have some practical implications becauseyou＊re never gonna work with an infinite series in practice.
You＊re always gonna workwith a finite approximation.
So the question is can you estimate the error?
If you＊re calledupon,
can you give some reasonable estimate for how far off you are?
Not just at a point,
but uniformly over the interval where you＊re interested in making the approximation.
Soit can come up.
So you have uniform estimate of the closeness.
Okay? All right.
So that＊s the continuous case and the smooth case.
So that＊s good news, all right? That＊sgood news.
That＊s nice.
If the function is continuous the series are converging.
If thefunction is smooth the series is converging and it actually,
sort of,
stays uniformly closeto the given function.
Now, I want to jump back, actually,
to the discontinuous casebecause there is one situation
that comes up often enough in practice that it＊s useful toknow about and that＊s
when you have a jump discontinuity.
And, again, I＊m not gonnaprove this,
but I think you should be aware of it and there＊s actually gonna be someproblems that use it,
or a problem that uses it. So if you have a jump discontinuity,
functions can fail to be continuous in a lot of different ways.
The simplest way a functioncan fail to be continuous
if it has a jump discontinuity like the first example that Ishowed.
So the example of a switch where it＊s on,
then off, all right? Something like this,
allright? Where the signal jumps down or up.
Okay? So EG. And there the theorem is,
thatis if a T knot is a point of jump discontinuity,
this is a really cool result actually. Thenthis converges,
then the sum minus infinity to infinity 每
well, yeah. I＊ll put it like this.Minus two pi I,
KT, sorry, sorry, sorry. F hat of K, the Fourier series,
F hat of K, E to thetwo pi I, KT does converge at T knot.
It converges at the jump discontinuity,
but thefunction doesn＊t really have a value of T knot,
because it jumps. But it converges,actually,
to the average value, all right?
It converges to the point in the middle of thejump,
to the average of the jump i.e. to one-half 每
let me write it like this one-half F of Tknot.
This is usually the way it＊s written. F of T knot plus F of T knot minus,
all right?
So what I mean by that is you＊re approaching T knot from the left,
that＊s F of T knotminus, it has this value.
You approach F of T knot from the right it has this value,
that＊s Fof T knot plus, all right?
They＊re two different values of jumps and if you look at theaverage of the jump,
right in the middle, that＊s what it converges to,
all right? Kind ofcool. And this wasn＊t proved until,
I think, the 1900＊s,
sometime in the early part of the1900＊s.
So this was way after Fourier had done his initial work
and people werestruggling with a lot of these problems.
And this is useful enough that it comes up inapplications.
So, for example, for the saw tooth, or not the saw tooth,
for the switchperiodic signal here,
if it jumps from zero to one then at a value of discontinuityconverges to one-
half, all right?
So even sometimes people define this function to be one on the interval from zero to one-
half, leaving out one-half. One-
half at the discontinuity and zero from here to here,
right?You sometimes see that definition given.
And the reason why people sometimes give thatdefinition is because they want to anticipate this result.
So if they want to use Fourier＊sseries, they say that that,
you know, it＊s, sort of,
consistent with the definition of thefunction in consistent
with the property of the convergence of the Fourier series.
This isnot so easy to prove, all right?
None of these things are really easy to prove.
It requires alot of work, all right?
It requires a lot of estimates and careful analysis,
but it＊s nice.
It＊svery satisfying in some sense that it tells you 每
at least you know what the situation is.
I＊m not saying it＊s easy to establish,
but at least you know what the facts are,
all right?That＊s good. That＊s good. Okay?
So any questions on that? This should be,
sort of, part of your vocabulary. Yeah?Student:
[Inaudible] continuity?Instructor (Brad Osgood):
Then that＊s not a jump discontinuity, all right?
What I meanby jump discontinuity,
I mean it jumps between two finite values.
Okay? Yeah. I＊mtrying to avoid 每 I mean,
I＊m talking to you in a somewhat informal way.
I＊m trying toavoid giving very precise definitions to all these things because you,
sort of, know itwhen you see it, all right?
You can do that, of course.
You can give very precisestatements here about the uniformity of approximation,
about how it converges, and soon, but that＊s not so crucial for us.
It＊s just you should know in general what the bigpicture is.
Yeah?Student:
[Inaudible] point that ever function with jumps,
so what about points wherethere are no jumps?
Instructor (Brad Osgood):Sorry?Student:
What about point where there are no jumps?
Instructor (Brad Osgood):All right.
What about points where there are no jumps?
So,actually, perhaps,
what I should have done is give a more careful statement of thecontinuous case.
The more careful statement of the continuous case is the seriesconverges at any point of continuity,
all right? So if a function 每 if it doesn＊t jump,
if it＊scontinuous at that point then the series converges at that point.
Okay?
So that wouldactually be a more precise statement of it.
Oh,
I better not stop asking for questions here,
all right? As I say,
I＊m trying to avoid the infinite regression of making the statements asprecise as I can.
I can do that, but you don＊t want to see that.
All right.And, again,
don＊t underestimate the effort that it took to do this,
all right?
When Fourierfirst came out with his ideas and we＊ll see that his original application,
actually, onMonday. He was very bold. He actually said any function,
not just any periodic function,
because he was thinking of extending a function to be periodic by just repeating it,
youknow. He was thinking of functions, which die ff and then repeating it.
So he madestatements like any function can be represented by such an infinite series.
And peoplewere scandalized by that,
especially if they were French and the French are easilyscandalized.
Bonjour, any function, you are a fool, monsieur.
So it caused a great deal of consternation
and it caused a lot of work to get done to try tosort these things out.
So don＊t underestimate the effort that went into getting even thismuch.
But now,
this was still ultimately not satisfying because Fourier really set hissights very high.
But any periodic phenomena, never mind smoothness,
whatever,
couldbe represented in some sense by a Fourier series,
by this sort of infinite sum.
And to sortthat out and to get to the truth of
that really required an entirely different perspective.
So Iwanted to say a little bit about that.
I＊ll only get to a little bit today and I＊ll finish it up onMonday,
and then we＊ll see some applications of this,
all right? All right.So general case. That is not talking about continuity,
not talking about smoothness, andso on, all right?
In here, what＊s really involved is you need,
we learned after decades,centuries of bitter experience,
you need a different notion of convergence of the infiniteseries.
You learn not to talk about what you think would be the most natural thing,
point-wise convergence, all right? You learned by hard lessons.
You learned it because it didn＊twork. I mean,
ultimately you couldn＊t get an answer that was very satisfying.
In thesecases we＊re fine,
but somehow under natural and fairly general situations,
you learned notto ask for convergence of a sum like this,
F hat 每
let me just put general coefficients inthere.
Cease of K, E to the two pi I, KTM. Even for general series,
all right?
You learn not to ask for convergence of that at particular points.
At values of T, all right?
You＊ve moved away from plugging in values of T
and looking at the series of constantsand asking whether or not converged,
all right? And that was a hard step to take.
Rather,
what was ultimately learned was you get a satisfying answer if you asked forconvergence in the mean,
convergence on average. I mean,
the proof that it was a goodidea are the results
that you can get if you take this point of view and it was a hard wonpoint of view.
So you get a better picture, more satisfying picture,
if you ask forconvergence in the average sense or also sometimes called convergence in the mean,
andI will write that down, all right?
In engineering terms it＊s also sometimes called convergence in energy.
You do see thisterm for reasons, which I＊ll explain,
probably not today, but next time. Okay?
Remindme. All right. Now, what does that mean?
Well,
you need to make some assumption onthe function,
all right?
It＊s not maybe completely general in a sense the function＊sarbitrary,
but the assumption you make on the function is pretty minimal.
So, again, I＊massuming the function＊s periodic.
So really everything takes place on the interval zero toone.
It＊s only the properties on the function on the interval from zero to one that mattersfor us
because everything is just repeated after that,
all right?So, I suppose, again, F of T is periodic period one,
periodic period one,
and you alsosuppose that it has the following property.
That the interval 每 it＊s square interval.
SquareDT is fine.
If the interval of the square of F is finite on the interval
and that＊s not too harda thing to insist on.
It＊s not too restrictive a thing to insist on.
There are functions thatdon＊t satisfy that.
If a function goes off to infinity at a certain rate on the interval fromzero to one,
if it＊s unbounded, then it may not satisfy this.
But certainly the functions thatcome up most often in applications
are gonna satisfy a condition like this and
thisactually is sometimes the hypothesis of finite energy for reasons
which we＊ll understanda little bit more later.
Take this interval,
it＊s often taken to be the total energy of thefunction depending on what the function represents.
And so you＊re assuming thatsomehow the signal has finite energy,
which is a reasonable physical assumption,
allright?Finite energy. All right. Then as it turns out,
then you conform 每 the Fourier coefficientsdo exist.
That＊s something that actually has to be proved separately because it＊s aquestion of integrability,
but it＊s true.
You conform the coefficients F hat of K equals theintegral from zero to one,
E to the minus two pi I, KT as before, F of T,
DT, all right?Again,
so that＊s actually now a separate issue that has to be verified
because you＊re notassuming the function is continuous or anything else,
but it can be done. And the punchline is,
and it＊s quite a punch line,
that you still get convergence of the series,
of theinfinite Fourier series, but not 每
and this board is floating up here. Let me do it over here.
But not by plugging in points,
but rather in an average sense as follows.
So then I＊ll write it like this. The interval from zero to one.
I want to look at how closethe function is to an approximating series,
so that means a finite version of the sum.
Sothe sum,
the interval of the sum from K equals minus N to N of F hat of K,
E to the twopi I, KT minus F of T squared,
DT, all right?
So I look at the average of the square of thedifference between a finite approximation of the sum,
makes perfect sense to form that,and the function.
And the statement is that this tends to zero as N tends to infinity,
allright?
The series converges of the function in the average sense.
The series converges tothe function in the mean,
all right?
The idea of integrating a function to get an average value is probably not so unfamiliar toyou 每
one second. The idea of integrating the square,
or the difference of the squares,
isalso probably more or less more familiar to you and,
as a matter of fact, this is exactly,again,
for reasons I can＊t explain today,
exactly related to the least squares approximationof a function by a combination of complex exponentials.
Now, you had a question?Student:
[Inaudible] convergence in the mean square?
Instructor (Brad Osgood):Pardon me?Student:
Is this mean square convergence?Instructor (Brad Osgood):
Yeah. Mean square convergence, thank you.
I sayconvergence to the mean,
maybe I should even call it mean square convergence.
If you＊refamiliar with that term by all means use it,
all right? So it＊s mean square convergence.
Allright. So the result is 每
that I＊m afraid we＊ll have to quit for today.
That the function 每 theseries converges to the function,
right? That is, it makes sense to write,
you write F of Tequals it＊s Fourier series,
K equals minus infinity to infinity, F hat of K,
E to the two pi I,KT,
but you have to understand what this equal sign means,
all right? In this context, allright?
In this context you have to be careful here what this equal sign means.
It doesn＊t meanpluck value of T and watch the series converge to the value of the function.
It does notmean that.
It means that if you compute that interval for a finite sum and let the degree goto infinity here,
then that interval will tend to zero.
The mean square difference will tendto zero.
That＊s what that equal sign means, all right?
That the difference between this anda finite approximation tends to zero
as the approximation gets better and better.
Thesquare, interval to square.Now, that was a big change of view,
all right?
That was a big change in attitude to adoptthat notion of equality,
that notion of convergence, and so on.
And it had profound farreaching consequences,
all right? And, again, it took a long time to sort out.
And we＊reout of time for today, so I can＊ tell you that.
So on Monday I want to wrap this up. Not inall the mathematical details,
only so far as to give you what the general picture is
becauseyou＊re gonna see it beyond this class.
You＊re gonna see people use this terminology,
usethese ideas well beyond what we do in here,
and it＊s really quite satisfying.
It＊s a reallyquite thorough and satisfying coherent picture,
all right? So more on that on Monday.
[End of Audio]Duration: